we're continuing our discussion of how
Clifford algebras can be used to build
Spinners in a previous video I said that
we can Define Spinners as members of
minimal left ideals in Clifford algebras
we've already defined what a Clifford
algebra is and in this video I'm going
to explain what a minimal left ideal is
in the first part of this video I'm
going to talk about projectors which are
also called item potents and in the
second part of this video I'm going to
talk about how projectors lead to ideals
I'm also going to give the definitions
of some algebraic structures like rings
and algebras along the way
so let's begin by talking about
projectors which are also called item
potents
I'll start by talking about projectors
used on vectors and this should match up
with your common sense idea of what a
projector does afterward I'll use this
idea to explain projectors in Clifford
algebras which is a little more abstract
let's say we have a vector v and some X
Y axes and let's say I want to project
this red vector v onto the x-axis
this would mean we project V down along
this dotted line onto the x-axis so that
only the X component remains
if I wanted to project this red V Vector
onto the y-axis we project V across this
dotted line onto the y-axis so that only
the Y component remains
now let's say I've projected a vector
onto the x-axis and I want to take the
result and project it onto the x-axis
again
our new result after the second
projection is unchanged it's the same
Vector we already started with
so the conclusion here is that doing a
projection once is the same thing as
doing that projection twice
converting this into symbolic language
if we have a projector P applying P once
should be the same thing as applying P
twice so P equals P Squared
this is the mathematical definition of a
projection operator also called an item
potent
let's look at some examples of Matrix
projectors
this Matrix here projects out a 3D
vector's Z component it sets the X and Y
components to zero and leaves the Z
component alone
you can check that this Matrix squares
to itself so applying it once is the
same thing as applying it twice
this other Matrix projects a 3D Vector
onto the X Y plane so that the Z
component is set to zero and the X and Y
components are left alone
this Matrix also obeys the same
projector property
now let's consider something else let's
say we've taken a vector and we've
projected it onto the x-axis
now let's take the result and project it
onto the y-axis
the result is that there's nothing left
we get the zero vector
the conclusion here is that when we
project a vector along two different
orthogonal directions we get 0 as a
result
we say that two projectors p and Q are
orthogonal if applying one and then the
other gives us zero
the two Matrix projectors we showed
earlier are orthogonal if we project
onto the z-axis and then project onto
the X Y plane there's nothing left and
we get zero
and as expected when we multiply these
two projection matrices we get the zero
Matrix
if we were to project onto the X Y plane
and then project onto the x-axis the
result is non-zero so these two
projectors are not orthogonal and they
do not multiply to give us the zero
Matrix
let's look at some projector properties
if we have a projector P then one minus
p is also a projector in the language of
matrices we can think of one as just
being the identity Matrix
we can show that 1 minus p is a
projector by showing that 1 minus P all
squared equals itself
as an exercise you can try pausing the
video and proving this property as well
as other upcoming properties before I
give the answer
after we distribute P Squared becomes P
since p is a projector
and here minus p and plus P cancel with
each other
this gives us 1 minus P which is the
original projector so this shows that 1
minus p is a projector
as an example if P projects onto the
z-axis then 1 minus P would be the
identity Matrix minus P which gives us
this projector onto the X Y plane
we can also prove that the projector's p
and 1 minus P are always orthogonal to
each other
we prove this by multiplying the two
projectors and showing that we get zero
after Distributing P Squared becomes p
and p minus P equals zero
indeed the projector onto the z-axis and
the projector onto the X Y plane are
orthogonal and multiply to zero
here's another property if p and Q are
orthogonal projectors then P plus Q is
also a projector again we can prove this
by showing P plus Q all squared is equal
to itself
after Distributing the PQ product terms
go to zero because they are orthogonal
and p squared equals p and Q squared
equals Q since they are both projectors
and we get p plus Q as desired
so for example a projector onto the
x-axis and a projector onto the y-axis
are orthogonal but if we add them
together we get a new projector onto the
X Y plane
finally I'm going to give a definition a
projector is called minimal if the
projector cannot be written as the sum
of other projectors so the X Y plane
projector is not minimal because we can
write it as the sum of other projectors
but the projectors onto the X and Y axes
are both minimal projectors because we
can't write either of these as a sum of
simpler projectors
we'll see later in this video that
minimal projectors are related to
minimal ideals
so to sum up a projector is an operator
p with the property that p squared
equals P two projectors p and Q are
orthogonal if p q equals zero each
projector P has an orthogonal projector
partner 1 minus p
the sum of two orthogonal projectors is
another projector and a projector that
can't be written as the sum of other
projectors is called minimal
also projectors are also called item
potents item potent is just a fancy word
for something that doesn't change when
you apply it multiple times
now what we've seen so far are Matrix
projectors that act on vectors this
should be pretty familiar to anyone who
knows linear algebra
next I'd like to talk about projectors
in Clifford algebras specifically we'll
look at projectors in cl30 which has
basis vectors Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma
Z that all square two plus one and all
anti-commute with each other
a member inside a Clifford algebra p is
called a projector if p squared equals p
let's take any unit Vector U in cl30
because vectors and Clifford algebra's
Square to their squared length U squared
equals one because it's a unit vector
the expression one-half times one plus U
is a projector
we prove this the usual Way by showing
that it squares to itself
we distribute and Since U squared equals
one we get two plus two U
H factoring the 2 out we can cancel it
with one of the factors of one-half
and we get one half times one plus u
which is the original projector as
desired
I'll call this projector p u Plus
its orthogonal projector partner 1 minus
pu plus is given by one-half times one
minus U I'll call this projector pu
minus
so any arbitrary unit Vector U and a
Clifford algebra will give us a pair of
projectors p u plus and P U minus
as a specific example we can look at the
Z unit Vector Sigma Z
if we look at the two by two Matrix
representation of the sigmas we know
that one is just the two by two identity
Matrix and sigma Z is just Z Z power
Matrix with entries 1 0 0 negative one
this gives us these two projection
matrices for p z plus and p z minus
let's take these projectors and apply an
arbitrary two by two Matrix to them from
the left
we see that pz plus has the effect of
projecting out the First Column and
setting the other entries to zero
likewise pz minus has the effect of
projecting out the second column and
setting the other entries to zero
notice that if we add these two
projections we get the original Matrix
back this is because when we add the two
projectors together we get one back
which is the identity Matrix which
doesn't change anything through
multiplication
so when we add the two Matrix
projections together we can factor out
the original Matrix and sum the
projectors to one which gives us back
our original Matrix
now here we've been looking at the 2x2
matrix representations of projectors in
cl30 now let's look at abstract members
of cl30 written out using symbols
so given any arbitrary multi-vector
element m in our Clifford algebra our
projectors pz plus and pz minus can
break M up into two pieces I'll call
these two pieces m z plus and M z minus
we can then add the two pieces back
together to get the original M since pz
plus and pz minus add to give one
the same is true for any pair of
orthogonal projector Partners they can
always be used to break up elements into
two pieces that can be added back
together again to give us the original
let's switch gears for a bit and talk
about ideals which is a concept that
comes up when studying rings and
algebras
Loosely speaking a ring is a set where
addition subtraction and multiplication
are all defined but we don't require
division to be defined
for example the integers form a ring
because we can add subtract and multiply
them to get more integers even though
dividing two integers doesn't always
give us an integer
matrices also form a ring because we can
always add subtract and multiply
matrices
division with matrices would be defined
as multiplication with a matrix's
inverse
but since not all matrices are
invertible we can't always do division
with matrices but that's okay because
division isn't required in rings
the definition of an algebra is a vector
space where addition subtraction and
multiplication of vectors are all
defined but we don't need division
between vectors to be defined
addition and subtraction come for free
in Vector spaces but Vector
multiplication is something extra that
needs to be defined
Clifford algebras are considered
algebras because the Clifford product
allows us to multiply vectors
the wedge product from Grassman
algebra's also allows a vector space to
become an algebra
now let's talk about ideals which are
special subsets of rings and algebras
an ideal is a special subset of a ring
or algebra that's sort of like a black
hole because ideals suck other ring
elements inside of them so that they
can't escape
I'll show you what I mean
let's take a look at the integers
specifically we'll look at the subset of
integers that are multiples of three
so negative six negative 3 0 plus 3 plus
6 and so on
the multiples of three are like a black
hole because once we get inside it's
difficult to escape
adding any two multiples of three
together will always give another
multiple of three for example three plus
nine equals 12 or 18 plus negative three
equals fifteen
also multiplying any integer by a
multiple of three gives us another
multiple of three for example seven
times three equals 21 and negative five
times three equals negative fifteen
so the multiples of three are a special
subset of the integers that's sort of
like a black hole the sum of any two
members in the set gives a result that's
still in the set
and the product of any integer with a
member of the subset will result in
another member inside the subset
the generalization of this pattern gives
us the definition of an ideal
an ideal I is a subset of a ring or
algebra where the sum of any two ideal
members gives us another ideal member
and the product of an ideal member with
any other element gives us another ideal
member
the multiples of three form an ideal
inside the integers because they satisfy
both of these properties
we can also look at ideals with matrices
let's look at this subset of two by two
matrices where only the First Column is
non-zero this is an ideal inside the
ring of two by two matrices
if we add two matrices of this form we
get another Matrix with only the First
Column being non-zero also if we
multiply a general two by two Matrix
from the left onto a matrix of this form
we get another Matrix where only the
First Column is non-zero
so these matrices form an ideal
note that this multiplication trick only
works if the general 2x2 matrix is
Multiplied from the left it doesn't work
if the Matrix is Multiplied from the
right
for this reason we call this subset a
left ideal since the multiplication
property is only satisfied if
multiplication is done from the left
if we look at the set of two by two
matrices where only the top row is
non-zero this ends up being a right
ideal because the multiplication rule is
satisfied only when matrices are
multiplied from the right
it turns out that any set of matrices
with only specific columns being
non-zero form left ideals and any set of
matrices with only specific rows being
non-zero form right ideals
so we have this abstract definition of
ideals but what do these ideal sets
really represent inside an algebra
to help give an intuitive understanding
of what ideals mean I'm going to use a
kind of metaphor or analogy you
shouldn't take what I'm about to say to
literally but it will hopefully help you
understand what ideals mean
in mathematics it's often useful to take
a complicated object and cut it up into
simpler pieces for example if we have a
three-dimensional Vector space one way
to cut it up into simpler pieces is to
introduce some XYZ axes this allows us
to take a vector and break it up into a
sum of X Y and Z components
when it comes to Rings ideal subsets are
sort of like the axes of the Ring they
allow us to break up members of the Ring
into smaller more basic pieces
for example in the ring of two by two
matrices we can break up a generic two
by two Matrix into two pieces one piece
where only the First Column is non-zero
and one piece where only the second
column is non-zero each of these pieces
represents a left ideal subset as we
showed earlier
these ideal subsets are sort of like the
axes of our ring we can add pieces from
our ideal subsets together to get any
arbitrary two by two Matrix
we could also break this ring up into
right ideal subsets where only the top
row is non-zero and only the bottom row
is non-zero
this can be thought of as a different
pair of axes for breaking up our ring
members into ideal components
now this axis metaphor doesn't work for
all ideals for example it does not work
for the multiples of three inside the
integers
but the metaphor does work if our ideal
is connected to a projector
and here is where we get to the main
point of this video where we bring
projectors and ideals together
if we find a projector inside our ring
or algebra it turns out that if this
projector acts on the entire ring or
algebra the resulting set will be an
ideal
in other words every projector in a ring
creates an ideal
recall the two projectors we defined in
the Clifford algebra cl30 which were pz
plus and pz minus
when we multiply a matrix M onto pz plus
from the left we get a matrix where only
the First Column is non-zero which is an
ideal subset and when we multiply a
matrix M onto pz minus from the left we
get a matrix where only the second
column is non-zero which is also an
ideal subset
so each of these projectors creates an
if we take the two projected ideals and
add them back together we get the entire
original space of two by two matrices
this is again related to the fact that
pz plus and pz minus add together to
give one
if we act on these projectors from the
right instead we get the top row ideal
and bottom row ideal instead which are
right ideals
let's go ahead and prove that projectors
lead to ideals recall that an ideal
subset must satisfy this addition
property and this multiplication
property
let's take a ring r with two orthogonal
projectors P1 and P2 where P1 and P2 add
2 1 and multiply to give zero
we get the set i1 from multiplying the
ring R onto the projector P1 from the
left and so i1 is a left ideal
let's first prove the addition property
two ideal members must add together to
give another ideal member if small R and
small s are members of the Ring then rp1
and sp1 are in the set i1
basically any member multiplied onto P1
from the left is defined as being inside
the set i1
adding these elements together gives us
small R plus small s times P1 which is
also in i1 by definition
now let's prove the left multiplication
property left multiplying any ring
member onto an ideal member gives us
another ideal member if small R and
small s are members of the Ring then rp1
is in the set i1 if we multiply from the
left by small s we get small s small R
times P1 which is also in the set i1 by
definition
so this proves that i1 is an ideal the
same reasoning can be used to show that
the set I2 equals R times P2 is an ideal
now an important fact is that two ideals
i1 and I2 share no members except zero
if their respective projectors are
orthogonal
in other words the intersection of Ideal
sets i1 and I2 is just the zero element
this makes sense with our axis metaphor
of ideals where the only place two axes
intersect is the origin or zero
however this is just a metaphorical
picture and we still need to actually
prove this is true
looking at our ring R the ideal i1 is a
subset inside of R if we take a bunch of
ring elements and project them using
projector P1 they will all end up inside
the ideal i1
let's take this element AP1 and give it
the name small r
remember projecting twice is the same
thing as projecting once so projecting
the ideal member AP1 again does not
change its value in other words
projecting an ideal member small R does
not change its value
now let's assume a ring member small R
belongs to two orthogonal ideals i1 and
I2 so projecting R using P1 doesn't
change its value and projecting small R
using P2 also doesn't change its value
so small rp1 equals small rp2
multiplying both sides by P1 on the
right P1 squared gives P1 and P2 times
P1 gives zero since they are orthogonal
so this means the projection of small R
is zero which means that small R itself
is zero since small R was already in the
ideal
this completes the proof that the only
member i1 and I2 have in common is zero
so the metaphor of axes for ideals is a
decent visualization the only element
that the axes have in common is the
origin zero and the only element that
ideals from orthogonal projectors have
in common is the Ring's zero element
finally note that it's possible for some
ideals to live inside other ideals as
subsets
Loosely speaking this is similar to how
we can project onto the X Y plane and
also project onto the x-axis but the
x-axis is a subset of the X Y plane
if an ideal has no sub ideals inside of
it we call it a minimal ideal
minimal ideals correspond to minimal
projectors which are projectors that
cannot be written as a sum of other
projectors
let's summarize everything we've learned
in this video projectors are operators
that square to themselves and two
projectors are orthogonal if they
multiply to give zero ideals are special
subsets inside rings and algebras that
are like black holes because ideals suck
other ring elements inside of them so
that they can't escape
addition and multiplication always bring
us back inside ideals
finally we learned that there's a
correspondence between projectors and
ideals and a projector that acts on a
ring or algebra will always give us an
ideal subset
when we have a set of orthogonal
projectors that all sum to one the
resulting ideals act like a set of axes
for our ring or algebra they break up
the ring or algebra into its most basic
components adding elements together from
different ideals gives us more General
members of the ring or algebra
finally minimal projectors are
projectors that cannot be written as a
sum of other projectors these correspond
to minimal ideals which have no ideal
subsets inside of them
we're going to see that elements of
minimal left ideals and Clifford
algebras correspond to Spinners in
particular the two by two matrices with
only the First Column being non-zero
behave essentially like the Pali
Spinners we saw used in quantum
mechanics and the Jones vectors used in
classical Optics that we saw in videos
two to five
however I'm going to need another video
to explain this so in the next video
I'll show how Spinners are members of
minimal left ideals in Clifford algebras